A Guide to the Edward Drewry Jervey Papers, 1961-1974
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Edward Drewry Jervey Papers, 1961-1974
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10049-a
This collection contains ca. 725 items (6 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Edward D. Jervey of Radford, Virginia, gave these papers to the Library on December 3, 1986.
Scope and Content Information
These papers contain depositions, other court decisions affecting teacher rights, correspondence, exhibits, minutes of meetings, briefs, printed material, jury lists, statements, subpeonas and other supporting documents, all pertaining to Dr. Jervey's 1972 suit against President Charles K. Martin and the Board of Visitors of Radford College concerning academic freedom.
These files came from the office of Philip J. Hirschkop, the attorney for Dr. Jervey in his suit, Edward D. Jervey, Plaintiff, v. Charles K. Martin, Jr., ET AL, Defendants, in the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia.
Organization
The collection has been organized into three series: 1) depositions, arranged alphabetically by the last name of the witness, 2) court decisions concerning teacher rights, and 3) exhibits and related documents.
Contents List
- SERIES I: DEPOSITIONS
  - Deposition of Dr. Edward P. Ambrose 1969 June 17 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Dr. John Grove Barker 1969 Nov 24 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Dr. John Grove Barker 1970 Nov 18 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of L. Lee Bean, Jr. 1969 Oct 1 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Miss Jane Dudley 1972 Jan 10 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Mrs. Joette Graham 1972 Feb 10 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Frances A. Hurlburt 1969 Jun 17 (Box 1)
  - Depositions of Dr. Edward D. Jervey 1969 Jun 16-18, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Deposition notes of Dr. Edward D. Jervey [ca. 1969] (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Louis Paschall Jervey, Jr. 1971 Feb 3 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Thora Joe T. Jervey 1971 Jan 28 (Box 1)
  - Deposition of Bernard Jump, Jr. 1971 Mar 8 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Louann B. Lewright 1969 Jun 17 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Dr. C.K. Martin, Jr. 1970 Jun 11-12 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Dr. C.K. Martin, Jr. 1972 Apr 24 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Daniel E. Marvin, Jr., Irving Silverman, and Franklin Hillman 1969 Sep 4 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Leonard G. Muse 1972 Jan 10 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Dr. Clifford C. Norse 1972 Apr 24 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Charles Hancock Reed 1972 Feb 11 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Charles Hancock Reed 1972 Oct 25 (Box 2)
  - Deposition of Mrs. Elizabeth L. Sumner 1972 Feb 10 (Box 2)
- SERIES II: COURT DECISIONS RE: TEACHER RIGHTS
  - Board of Trustees of the Los Angeles Junior College District v. Metzger ca. 1971 (Box 3)
  - Drown v. Portsmouth School District 1971 (Box 3)
  - Duke v. North Texas State University 1971 (Box 3)
  - Gouge and Klein v. Joint School District No. 1 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Hoag v. Board of Trustees of the Los Angeles Junior College District 1970 (Box 3)
  - Johnson v. Branch 1966 (Box 3)
  - Keefe v. Geanakos 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Keyishian v. Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York 1967 (Box 3)
  - Lucas v. Chapman 1970 (Box 3)
  - Lucia v. Duggan 1969 (Box 3)
  - Mailloux v. Kiley 1971 (Box 3)
  - Oliphant v. New Mexico Junior College Board 1969 (Box 3)
  - Orr v. Trinter 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Parducci v. Rutland 1970 (Box 3)
  - Roth v. Board of Regents of State Colleges ca. 1972 (Box 3)
  - Sindermann v. Perry 1970 (Box 3)
  - Smith v. Losee 1972 (Box 3)
  - Stewart v. Pearce 1971 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1969-1972 (Box 3)
- SERIES III: EXHIBITS & RELATED DOCUMENTS
  - Board of Visitors Meeting Minutes 1969 (Box 4)
  - Brief re Dr. Edward D. Jervey's suit against Dr. C.K. Martin [ca. 1969?] (Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Dr. Jervey with Michael Grossman and the American Association of University Professors 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Dr. C.K. Martin's files 1961-1969 (Box 4)
  - Educators Negotiating Service Newsletters 1971 (Box 4)
  - Evidentary Material ca. 1961-1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Exhibits 1961-1969 (Box 4)
  - Jury List 1971 (Box 5)
  - Meeting on Committee on Academic Tenure 1971 Apr 13 (Box 5)
  - National Education Association File and Jervey's correspondence with NEA, ACLU, AAUP, and B. Jump 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - Printed Materials 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Report to the Committee on Academic Freedom and Tenure of Radford College 1968 (Box 5)
  - Statement Before Dean's Committee re the Grievance of Professor William K. Hale 1971 (Box 5)
  - Statements 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Subpoenas 1972 (Box 6)
  - Witnesses Interviewed 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Witnesses Not Interviewed ca. 1972 (Box 6)